okay here we go uh so if you
meditate it will be on one thing only
and that's the meaning of
meditation so again we're going to try
to sort of emulate the Saka tradition
which big gup Lama advises of trying I
thought it'd be fun to try to do 18
short sessions in a day see how it goes
so we're going to do a session right
now but first you have to do a book
that's good luck
takes last time and know you have to do
the positive
okay let's start
um let's start with a short meditation
okay start by watching your breath post
your Sentry at the tip of your
nose end of the nocl watch the breath
come and go stay there one place that's
vitation
one
e
e e
picture a sun picture a sunfill
mo on the top of a
mountain the side of a mountain near
the there golden sunlight streaming into
the windows
sky above to the window you can see sky
sky soft
Mountain Rising right up
imagine that your heart teach with
you placing you sitting on the ground
pring in the sunlight
visualization is not making photographs
or paintings or sculptures visualization
is bringing a living being into the room
with
you eyes blinking chest
breathing one from your
body e
and just focus on their face just the
outline of their
face now start to go into meditation
which means one object only not aware of
the sunlight anymore not aware of the
sky
anymore just aware of
their your mind link to their no other
thing in the
world
e e
just a
IND you can slowly open your
head so we said that uh meditation is
just a
tool uh like a microscope or a telescope
and then you have to train you have to
train it on something you have to put
something in
your under your
microscope you have to want to see
something
larger uh so then there comes into the
play very crucial part of meditation
which is selecting your object okay
selecting the thing that you will
meditate
upon uh
and we are this is Pon Chase L room okay
it's a thousand
Pages uh very very famous and I was
sitting uh with someone recently at
lunch and everybody was saying there
what they thought was the greatest book
of all time you know the Bible came
up gone to the
wind I said no I'm the lock
this book is called me me means
Liberation l means hand CH is s for CH
which means
uh right here like somebody you just
kind of say here's liberate you know and
you just take it I give it to you okay
like that somebody what do you call
it yeah it's the gift of Liberation
trust into your head and they just say
here take it like a potato you know and
you're like wow so
uh that's the name of the book
uh it's a teaching that was given in I
think
uh for 24
days in the capital
of uh by my teachers teachers teacher
okay ISR and he trained the teacher of
the current di so he he an amazing llama
and he trained
K who's the teer of the current D teer
was my teacher's teacher also
so my teacher uh taught this book
for over 25 years we went through it
three times uh and it's a beautiful
beautiful
uh
manual uh of of all the steps to
Enlightenment so like when you buy
lawnmower and they say try to read the
manual and you know you throw it out no
no and you uh you read what you have to
read you know you read the what it call
what's it called the short instructions
you know and there's like 10 steps you
know like screw on the blade you know
put the oil in and like that and then
you can mow your lung so this is a l Rim
text uh L means path Rim
means step
step by step so step by step on the path
to Enlightenment the idea being that
there are certain
realizations that everyone needs if they
are going to get enlightened okay uh for
example the realization of our own
impermanence okay it has to come home to
you very strongly if you hope to get
enlightened you have to have an
experience or or some
thing understanding a close friend dies
or or something like that you know these
are necessary for Spiritual Development
you must
have uh some kind
of realization of impermanence thrust
upon you uh in order to progress
spiritually someone who thinks they're
going to live forever or or someone who
hasn't had a tragedy in their life it's
much harder for them uh to develop
spiritually
so this book has all of those steps and
uh the assertion is that you must go
through all those steps if you Skip One
or skip
two spiritually speaking it would be
like leaving a major part out of a car
so you know my teacher had a book bug it
had 200,000 miles on it it broke one day
he said fix it because you're you're
American you can fix
it uh and
uh I took it apart and I put it back
together and there were three pieces
Miss I had three pieces left you know
and then I'm like I tried to start it it
wouldn't start because no car company's
going to put a piece in there that costs
anything that's not necessary you know
so
uh it's the same with lri okay it's the
same with your spiritual life there are
certain uh experiences inner experiences
that you that you cannot do without you
must have them uh and so the the process
of going to L is to try to take us
through those experiences in a logical
way so that by the end we become
enlightened
uh so
we're that's how much we
haven't
done okay in the last class meaning I
skipped 950 Pages or something and I
took you to the end why uh the end of
the process of Liberation involves a lot
of meditation you have to be meditating
a
[Music]
lot and then you must train that tool
upon emptiness you must try to grasp
emptiness if you understand emptiness
then all things are possible if you
don't then nothing is possible so
additionally in Long R Emptiness is
taught
last uh and meditation is taught just
before that okay but I I I what I want
you guys to do is I'm taking you through
meditation
first uh which is basically the nine
levels and the how many Powers six six
powers and the four states of mind so if
you don't come out of any with anything
else this week it's got to be what n six
and four and then you can spend the rest
of your life trying to remember what
they were
uh and then to train that thing on
emptiness and then Emptiness is the key
to everything so my my
proposal which you don't have any choice
but to accept is uh we'll do the
meditation first which is what we're
doing and then we'll study emptiness as
we as we go
and then we will train that emptiness
meditation is
a is a gun with a telescopic site okay
like I used to hunt deer like in Arizona
when I grew up you had to hunt deer and
you know we were brought up I had 257
magnum and I was trained from age 10 to
shoot these guns and then the the beer
one it has a telescopic site on the cup
and then it has it's a high power very
high power raffle so you could hit a
deer on another
Mountain uh so you can think which I he
did once and then I I told my dad I
can't do that anymore that's was another
story um but the telescope is the
meditation you see the telescope is the
meditation the scope and then the the
power is the gun the gun is emptiness
okay so if you combine them right if you
have uh uh good if you have really
powerful meditation
scope and then you have the rifle which
is
emptiness then you can get enlightened
see
uhana and shamata in Sanskrit okay
shamata is the shabata is Ultimate
capacity to meditate past level n okay
and then the gun is is
called which means an extraordinary
insight to how things work so
so uh we need to combine those two you
have to have the gun and you have to
have the scope so what we're doing this
week is I'm giving you the gun in the
scope okay and then you got to go shoot
things
okay uh what are you going to shoot
you're going to train that gun and that
scope on the Lum r on the steps of the
path to Enlightenment you see so each
time we go through a step starting in
the
spring uh you'll train the gun on that
you see so let's say the first let's say
we do a step which is called death
meditation or study a person's
impermanence so then we will instead of
just doing the normal om thing which is
you say okay everybody has to die
there's nine reasons why you should come
to four conclusion you know instead of
doing that we will train that gun on
death itself and we will do a death
meditation then you will go through the
death training but then you'll train the
gun on it and say do you have to die you
know can you can you change that you see
because it's empty and if you had enough
concentration you could change the fact
of your mortality okay if you understood
it
emptiness uh and if you could focus
strongly enough you could you could
shoot your own morality you see right in
Yogi
termsand means
what take a stick to death
d means sck means death so
the that's my I think it'll be very
become very popular way to teach and you
will be the first teachers of it okay
which means you have to learn it so the
whole context of what I'm doing is that
I want each person here to
teach to teach starting the day after
you leave okay the day when you could
start talking with e uh start teaching
okay so so take notes and pay attention
as if the lineage rested on your
shoulders which it does okay for 2 and a
half thousand years each each group of
students has taken responsibility to
pass it on
correctly accurately and then that's
your job once in our tradition in our
lineage uh once you listen to a teaching
it's your job to know it well enough to
pass it on so you got to make sure you
get it down
Pat okay you can even ask questions for
the next 24
hours uh we let's say you can ask
questions by note throughout the week
okay but but you should know it with a
with a confidence of a
teacher like if somebody lost the
instructions to the lawnmower they
should be able to come to you and say
well what do we do what did the book say
so take enough notes that you can pass
it on responsibly okay you can be
irresponsible and just say I'm I used to
do that some some of my years in my 30
years I'd say oh I'm just going to osid
it from the Llama you know I don't
remember too much of those years
so I would suggest
notes okay so take notes and then in the
evening session we'll start in the
poster and I I don't mind if you make
notes on the poster and then my hope is
that you would stick the poster up at
home when you get home home and it's
always looking at you in a accusatory
way you know like look at all these cool
levels when she didn't have time to read
me today or do me
today we had a poster in the y in the
tri Retreat L chris9 we we hung it from
one of the lower sticks and you had to
bump into it to get out of the door and
it was some kind of blessing you know
and uh so what I wanted to do in the
evening sessions you'll be taking your
notes on your poster because the poster
is outline it's not complete and then
and then you take it home and you sit
with the poster you put it up
somewhere some the New Yorkers will have
to get a larger
apartment okay all
right so we're going through emptiness
but we're picking up where we left off
in October November I don't know but
anyway we can't go
on we have to do it this way I've
realized we have to do it this way we'll
be having teaching every meditation Tre
because otherwise we can't finish in 10
years it would take 20 years so let's do
10 years okay we can do something else
all right so just for the record of the
video and all that I believe we're at
365 B last line okay so I'll read the
toess of blessing and then I'll teach it
to you we're on the subject
of okay
if you're going to learn
emptiness so probably as my teacher gu
your te Eng would say you should
probably have two sections in your
notebook one is going to be for the
meditation stuff and one is going to be
for the emptiness stuff so we're doing
The Emptiness
stuff
uh every object by the way if you
haven't heard anything about emptiness
in your life don't worry okay you came
at the right time okay uh we're starting
from the
start every object in the
world every existing thing has its own
emptiness okay
uh what's the easiest way for us to get
at any one of those you see if we can
just grasp one of
them we can get liberated we can change
death itself out of all the stuff in the
world what would be the the coolest
emptiness to start from like the
emptiness of snow or The Emptiness of
dinner or The Emptiness of my last
distraction in my meditation see
everything has emptiness so the text
says let's use
me that's the most powerful place to
start that's Michael will use Michael
rapael uses rapael Gabrielle uses
Gabriel you know you start like that you
use me I use mine and you
use you know you ever uses their own s
right that's the place to
start it's easier to start there he says
therefore we will start there we will
start the teaching from
there there are in classical Buddhist
teaching many ways to prove emptiness
okay and one famous way is called
dependent origination which you can just
think of in in human terms as everything
in the world had something that made it
happen Okay
like everything has something that came
before it and caused it that's all if
you see smoke there must be a fire you
know if you see a person there must have
been a mother okay just everything is
impelled by another thing that's
all that's how Buddha taught pagination
he only used one silver words but
improved uh he said stuff happens
because other stuff happens okay this
this happened because that happen all
right and we don't understand what
causes stuff we we we say uh snow falls
because I blew my nose or something like
that like what the way we believe things
work is as ridiculous as saying snow
falls because I blew my
nose maybe it will if you're really
close to the this where I'm sitting
okay there are many many ways he says
you can use pen origination things
happen because of other
things or you can use Numba these are
seven
variations on a study of what is the
relationship between Mike and Mike's
Parts what is the relationship between
Michael and Michael's arms and Michael's
legs and Michael's head Michael's M okay
and we finished that in Phoenix okay we
did nothing we did we
used on the last
thing the example
of something in the parking lot a car
okay we used a car and it took a long
time I I checked the tapes because I I
needed to know where to start today and
it's like an hour on the the parts of a
car okay
that I just want you for the record I
want you to know that's not the whole
that's not the whole argument but it
took a couple hours and that was enough
there are six more variations okay which
we're not going to get to because that's
not the purpose he's just mentioning it
saying there are many ways to
Pro so means
ET those who are just starting out on
their study of emptiness it would be
easier for them if they used the
classical argument for emptiness called
it's not one and it's not many okay chck
to say
chick many neoy editors have corrected
the to to to because after Ka the
locative required is to and they didn't
understand then it was Chang
meaning one and many okay
so meaning uh things are not one and
things are not many okay is this is this
one clock or many
clocks it's one clock okay are are these
one clock or many clock yeah those are
more than one okay and but that's a
classical proof for emptiness where you
prove that there's not one clock in this
room and there's not two clocks in this
room either and there's no other choice
it's either one clock in this room or
there's more than one clock in this room
and there's no other choice okay you
covered everything can I say that either
there's one clock in this room or
there's if there's any clocks in this
room okay there's either one or there's
many okay can we say that yeah so that's
a classical proof of emptiness how
that's true why that's true he's going
to get
there but he says inan means
one and only sometimes you see one and
only it can can mean one and only like
he's saying Capital we do it with a
capital T the city
is where where's the
City Phoenix
yeah okay everybody knows that okay no I
mean they say that I used to think it
was very arrogant when I first moved to
New York the city I said which city
okay uh
so think of CHA the proof of one or many
is the is the proof of emptiness he's
saying
okay
means okay J J mumo and many of those
who have followed in his
footsteps of his of his thinking lineage
okay we have to Divi divide between a a
political lineage and a thinking
lineage lots of followers of tonapa
aren't gas and lots of gas aren't okay
all
right so lots of followers of and
himself they used
uh what you say
a four what you call bullet point I
guess Nate crucial points four crucial
points bullet points okay to in regard
to the proof of emptiness based on one
in many okay so there are there are
four steps that you once I take you
through these four steps you should have
a really good grasp with emptiness all
right that's the point
n n they they they applied four crucial
points to the argument of one and
many
means hey you want to know the first
one the first crucial step for any
person who seeks to understand emptiness
and thereby save their
Planet uh is gaka okay say
gaka a lot of new students say
gacha it's G
J gacha means when I say my pocket is
empty I I'm talking about something
that's not there right which is
normally money
okay and there's a process of
discovering it you go to the restaurant
you tell everybody you're paying you uh
eat a big dinner at coacha
r coina rustia
in near
Sedona because you want to be a big shot
and you say you're going to pay for
everybody and then everybody eats a huge
meal and then uh they come they bring
the bill and you with a flourish you
reach into your pocket and then you're
like oh I gave my credit card to the
people doing the readings for the last
Phoenix
teaching and they lost the credit card R
that's another subject
uh um so I you reach in and there's this
sense
of emptiness okay uh but emptiness
implies The Emptiness of some something
has to not be there okay dcha means the
thing that emptiness is empty up Daka
means the thing that ain't
there daa that's if you don't know the
thing that ain't there you can't if you
don't know what a credit card is you
can't
what you can't discover that it's not
your pocket there's got to be something
that isn't there that you discover isn't
there and then it saves your life and
the lives of everybody on the planet
okay so that's gaka G so the first
crucial point is we must identify what
it is that's not
there and was never there okay and was
never there I like to talk about I was
driving down Fifth Street in how New
Jersey one night it was getting dusk I
had I was in ri's Honda which lasted 25
years cuz he never drove it and
uh and a and a mouse ran across the
street and I slammed on my brakes and I
I almost put my head to the windshield
you know like my head bumped the
windshield and then I was like oh I hope
I didn't hit him you know and I looked
down and it's an oak leaf that was
blowing in the wind right
so get this try to grasp this a thing
that wasn't what I thought it was almost
killed me okay a thing that wasn't what
I thought I was almost crushed my head
and and killed me left you know sent me
on into another world you know I was
reacting to a thing that didn't even
exist okay all right and that's what our
life is all about every everything you
ever got happy about everything you ever
got sad about every crisis you ever had
every problem you ever encountered every
person you didn't like all the lines on
your
face especially
these they theyve been produced by
something that didn't even exist and you
just made a boo boo it was a big boo boo
if the person you were mad at wasn't
there in a certain way okay uh the leaf
you tried not to run over wasn't wasn't
even was never there okay all the stress
of your life has been produced by a
mirage something that wasn't there
that's gcha gcha is the mouse running
across the road on the day that I slamed
my back on okay gacha is the mouse
running across the world on the day I
time my bre and in my mind you got to
put quotation marks
around
what mouse it was the
mouth that I almost ran over right we in
English we put quotation marks on things
that don't exist you know he's supposed
to be a competent boss you know you know
and we go like that right we have this
mudra there's a mudra there's
a uh you know actually all bosses are
incompetent that's why I don't have one
um
anyway Mouse okay mic
mic okay the mic that I've been
protecting and fighting for and you know
combing what hair had laugh you know
this might okay so this is Goa we must
establish who it was that wasn't there
when we had all our crisises in life
okay very famous say
[Music]
one of the most famous lines
from
last
from yeah in
English yeah Guide to
[Music]
the uh until you
can uh
try to make it common how you can make
contact
with the thing that you were imagining
you will never be able to realize that
it was never there until you can
identify the thing you thought was there
you will never be able to establish that
it never was there okay basically you
have to figure
out what is it you're thinking wrong
about Michael or Helen or
Ellen it's the
okay you know uh or anybody else what
what is it about Michael that I'm doing
wrong that's the big question now one
day I just sat down rib I said rib we're
in the class right he said yeah I said
the door's over there right he said yeah
I said so what am I doing wrong I'm
going to walk through that door and go
make you tea in about 2 minutes so what
am I thinking wrong about the door just
tell me let's just get it straight you
know just tell me and don't teach me all
this stuff you know just tell me what
I'm doing wrong with the door and I'll
stop doing
it okay like just tell me what I'm doing
wrong how am I thinking wrong about Mike
and and just tell me and then I'll stop
okay but unfortunately you have to
listen to scripture else I don't have
anything to do
okay so Master Shan said we must figure
out what it is that we're doing wrong
what is it that's not there that we
think is there cuz some of the stuff we
think is there is there Michael's here
he's teaching it's real okay but but
you're doing something wrong somehow
your your mind is what you call it what
you call when they adulterated right
there mixed in something unreal
[Music]
okay if you can't identify the me that
doesn't exist and the me which we have
to cancel mentally
[Music]
then we will not be able to cancel
it there's two kinds of cancellation in
in
Buddhism one is to prove that something
doesn't exist and one is to prove that
something is is not
something uh meok means to establish
that something doesn't exist
[Music]
he says if you can't see the target how
can you hit it with the arrow or we got
a high power rifle right how can you hit
the
target how can you hit the deer if you
can't see the deer right if you can't
identify what it is you're doing wrong
how are you going to shoot it okay that
frame that that thinking
okay or if you don't know the identity
of the criminal how you going to what
you call apprehend them
possible if you don't know the thing
that Emptiness is empty up and you don't
know what it is you're doing wrong with
the door then how are you going to stop
yourself
okay you must identify the mic that
doesn't
exist must identify the Michael or
everybody John has to do John no
everybody Gabel John the do the other
John okay I
he's going to give three
synonyms for the mic that doesn't exist
okay he's going to give three technical
words that are used to describe the mic
that doesn't exist here's the first one
de unreal
unreal CH he says the real and
unreal the real in unreal got
it and the nature in natural when you
say things are
not the nature in natural when you say
things are not natural right
when I say things are not natural what
is what am I referring to what is nature
when I say when I say things are unreal
what would real be like okay and then
the third one run this is easier
okay doesn't come from its own side it
doesn't come from its own side it
doesn't come we were in China for months
doing pens and and going like this and
this you know do you know that if you on
T you heard it 48 times
John okay you hold up you give the
argument about the entrance of the pen
then you hold up the pen in front of a
thousand people and you say is the pen
coming this way or is the pen coming
this way and then all these people say
the pen is going coming this way you
know they all get it right so R dupa
means coming this way towards you okay
towards you from from its own side inbet
is existing to it from its own side
so the own side in existing from its own
side the real in unreal and the the
nature in not natural these are all
got
okay all
right okay those are three different
ways to talk about it but we'll go more
don't worry if you're feeling lost it
means you have something of value
okay hopefully okay uh
sh the commentary to the 400 vers is
written by
Arya DEA who was the primary
student himself he
[Music]
says you want to know what it means when
they say Mike is not Mike okay get used
to that okay Mike is not Mike the
building is not the building the retreat
center is not the retreat center the
snow is not the
snow the mic that you're talking about
when you say that mic is not M okay what
does that mean he
says him me self M what we mean when we
say the mic that's not there is a mic
that wouldn't depend on anybody else or
anything anything else okay a mic that
could come without its proper causes a
mic that could exist without without
being in relationship to anything else
okay that's the mic
that doesn't exist okay that's the mic
that was never there that's the mic that
I've been protecting my whole life that
made all the wrinkles on my face okay
and if I hadn't believed in that mic I
my face wouldn't have those wrinkles I
would be happy all
okay I've been slamming on my breaks my
whole life for something that didn't
exist a mic and if I ask you to describe
what that mic would be like you could
start by saying a mic that could exist
without depending on anything else what
that means exactly we have to talk
about you could say that exists without
his mother or exists without you know
the experiences of his life or something
like that but we're going to go deeper
on it okay
uh that's how Master ARA
described the word no self no self means
no mic means no mic that ever happen
without relying on something
else
CH we'll do a
meditation I I want to keep throwing in
five minute
meditation this is the old Sak system
let's see how it works instead of a
2-hour thing where you space out for an
hour and 50
minutes and your knees hurt let your
need turn anyway okay
go back to your bread
just one thing nothing
else there's nothing else in the world
go back to the sunit room on the side of
the mon
the teacher is sitting with you
G upon their
FA they're looking at
you g upon their eyes there's nothing
else in the world you have no other
things to think about you have no other
worriors in the world you have no
plans no other
thoughts nothing else to feel or be
aware just connect with their eyes and
their face upon you stable
just stay there take your
sustenance see how it feeds your spirit
your mind and your body just stay on one
thing
feel some kind of or relief that you can
just stay on
one don't have to worry about inup just
be there
teacher not saying anything they're not
doing
anything looking at each
other just be content to be there that
contentment will make you will make you
a different person in
a e
did your teach your
farewell back
this and open your eyes
something that would not depend on it
causes other other things
something that existed from its own
side he's going to talk later about the
importance of experiencing these things
and not just learning the technical
lingo like it can become technical lingo
you can start saying it doesn't exist
from its own side and then you have you
have no personal feeling or experience
of what that means so I'm going to run
it by you just quickly okay
which is why it's taking so long to get
[Music]
this so this is the you know DCI
tour way she heard it 5,000 times she
translated
it
uh
uh what's this thing we'll do it real
fast what's his thing
if a dog comes in here and I wave it at
a dog and I hand it to you know I go
like this what will they do they'll chew
on it they won't see a pen they don't
see a pen they see something to chew
chew to you can say
okay who's
right yeah you could say both okay it's
okay it's a it's it's really a pen to a
person and it's really a
two
okay if I leave the object here on the
seat and we all leave all the humans and
all the dogs leave which one is
it
yeah
NE we had two two people in the audience
in uh where's a it's so beautiful uh
there was a man sitting next to a lady
and
uh when I asked which one is it then the
the guy right the guy went like this so
he was Kong sing Kong sing means uh
emptiness in in Chinese right and then I
said
well so is it
coming so is it coming this way or is it
coming this
way yeah it must be coming this way
because a dog doesn't see a pen if it
were coming this way then a dog would
see a pen you see if it were coming from
its own
side it's such a simple proof and it
doesn't take 4,000 pages of scripture
you know uh if it we're coming this way
which is how we normally think of it you
see when you say it exists from its own
side you you you you hold to that idea
that it's a
pen right especially when it's
threatened by a dog and they chew on it
and you say don't chew on head the dog
is
like what are you doing using a
perfectly good ch to scratching on paper
all day they also get upset at us you
see you are misusing a chw toy why you
could be enjoying you know you see
really really you laugh because you the
extent to which it seems humorous to you
is the extent to which you believe it's
you
see it's not coming this way because of
the dog and the human thing it is coming
this I hate thr a big Ro what's the
ontological status of a pen that comes
this way what's the how much does a pen
that comes this way
exist zero okay that's empty right
that's
all that's the pen it doesn't exist this
whole scripture is going to go into this
long thing and okay I think we do
believe that things come this way and
the amount to the amount to which you
giggle when we talk about the dog saying
don't scratch on the paper with my two
toy is the extent to which you believe
it comes from
itself all right
uh so throughout this text I have a
little I have several bones to what do
you called to choose no bones to pick
with the traditional scripture and one
is that they throw around this thing
that about it not coming from causes but
really they're only talking about one
cost which is
what yeah my my perception that I lay on
it pen okay I have a seat in my mind and
and that forces me to see it as a pen so
in in China we had everybody was going
either this way and that was Mr Kong
Shing and next to him was a lady and she
kept going like this which is Mrs
Chong right is that right ch see
J don't look at me like that I say
Chinese and the go and then they they
try to guess what I'm trying to say and
then
oh what's the right word to
say anyway we had Mrs junga and we had
Mr kongin Right and Mrs junga kept going
like this and Mr kongin kept going like
that okay and that's all you just need
Mr King and Mr J and then you have it
okay this is not a pen for its own time
and whatever pen I see is coming from
the SC in my mind okay this and and this
and that's everything okay so so when
they keep seeing in the text the pen
origination depends on its own
causes you got to keep in mind that
they're talking about a a Jun okay and
they're not talking like you came from
your mother that's not a big Discovery
you know that it hasn't saved you you
know what I mean uh I mean I have a bone
to pick with the scriptures because they
keep saying depends on other factors and
you're like I know I depend on I eat I I
was born I drive a car I people help me
you know and but that's not the point
the point is there's a seed in your mind
she's making you see stuff as stuff
she's also making you see your own death
and if you could remove that
seed if if things are coming from seeds
all things are possible if things are
coming this way nothing's possible you
might as well shoot yourself my brother
did you know if it if it's all coming
this way you can't change it if it's
coming this way you just tweaking here a
little bit okay
how be nice to other people okay here we
go
sh means stands on its own okay
independent of
my you're from another
place where are you
from where are you
from which
part okay okay so I have to remember all
the accents okay
so uh is the is the SE It's Kind when
means means the pen could stand there on
its own without this okay the pen could
be there on its own without
that's like saying when you said it here
in the dog's ground the hum's ground
it's still a pen okay all right means
that
[Music]
selfing there he got to the part he said
you can talk about this in words and you
can teach this in a class
and in a debate you can you can roll out
you know the thing is not self-standing
but the thing depends on its Factor you
know you can when you're in a debate
ground or with an intellectual scholar
or you're teaching a class you can throw
around these terms he says
but but if you don't in your actual life
identify what the thing is that's self
standing if you can't do it with a
pen okay in your real life
G you'll never find the gaka get it down
to something in your real life you know
you can use the words when you're
teaching you can say it's self-existent
it's not self-existent you know or you
could say it depends on the pen
origination or it doesn't not
self-standing but at some point you got
to have a picture of a pen that could be
a pen without you thinking of it as a
pen because that's the cause they're
talking about okay it's not that it
wasn't it's not that you never
understood it was made in a fact you you
understood that uh they're talking about
the ultimate C which is your mind making
it at pen okay all
right is a pen which is made by the Mind
unreal no a pen which is not made by the
mind is unreal get it okay if there was
a pen that you could write with it
wasn't coming from your mind that would
be
impossible to say that it's coming from
your mind is finally to admit the
reality that it has and it's a
functional reality I can draw a Saddam
Hussein mustache on you if you want if
anyone doubts the reality of this
mindmade thing you know because it's
made by the mind it works if it weren't
made by the mind it couldn't work get
used to it
okay because then you can plant the
seeds in your mind for anything you want
that's the point you got to go one more
step right you can't just say it's
coming from your mind you got to say
well if you wanted five pens you could
just plant five pens or if you wanted $5
million you could just plant $5 million
or if you wanted a new husband or
upgrade your current husband you could
just do that inside your head and you
see uh just replant the seed okay it's
very cool okay if things are coming from
their own side nothing's
possible okay uh Dr
[Music]
sorry a person who wanders around with
words like oh self-existent and
dependent origination and blah blah blah
but doesn't get it with a pen okay
they're he says they're like a person
who says I was robbed yesterday and the
police say could you describe the the
thief and you say it was a guy and he
had a shirt on
okay like that's not enough okay they
haven't identified the GTA okay like how
are they going to apprehend this guy how
are they going to catch this guy if all
you can say about him is he had a shirt
on and he had two legs and and two arms
you know that's like throwing around
self-existent or comes from its own side
or depend ination okay that's like the
same as saying he was a guy if you don't
have a personal experience it that's
what he's making the point you got to
get to know the gaka what do you call it
up close and
personal
okay so don't just uh sit and listen to
what other people how they describe
emptiness or the Goa or don't just means
don't just throw around these
generalizations Ori or just uh general
concepts G okay don't be like
that he says you have to come into a
naked into that is called genter gure
means naked Buck Naked experience gure
means Buck Naked okay it does mean that
it means some just you open the door and
the guy standing here you know you're
sorry
okay that's g g means totally nak you
know and you got to come to a
g encounter with the gaka okay it's got
to be personal you're like wow I get it
okay it's not like it's throwing around
these words you know oh
self-existence I think self-existent is
self-existent okay uh go
[Music]
if you never have a personal experience
of what it is that's not there which was
what the pen that came from the pen you
can say it that way if it makes you
comfortable pen that comes from the
pen I like that that comes from
the you can use all the Buddhist proofs
in the world for emptiness that you want
means
uhen means there's a danger that you
will fall
into
uhaa means an overreaction to a teaching
on
emptiness an overreaction to a teaching
on EMP how would you describe that how
would that kind of person act after
that yeah they but think that nothing
was real and then what would
happen they'd either give up or they'd
go out and have a beer or you know
they'd go get smashed because what the
hell you know that rache when he got to
this point he used to quote Budweiser
commercials because he watched a lot of
baseball
um but it was One Life to Live drink
drink now One Life to Live you know like
people who fell into the people over
what do you call overreacted to a
teaching on emptiness they go out and
say well nothing matters you know
everything's empty I got an email from a
guy in Europe like two days ago and he's
like oh guess what I figured it out you
know nothing matters you know and I'm
like no it's the opposite if
everything's empty you got to be a good
person because that's where everything's
coming from okay the reaction of a
well-educated emptiness student should
be oh dang I got to be more careful I
have to be more nice okay it should be
the opposite cha means overreaction of
an undereducated emptiness sir okay uh
tenda means tend sha can mean either you
disregard dependent origination but
tenda can also mean uh tenda can mean
getting off to a good start like when
you meet a llama you offer a bow of a
fruit right and there's a famous
incident I think it was no I don't
remember he offered an empty ball and he
tenda tenda means he blew it he blew the
what you call it
auspiciousness he he blew it on the
first day he offered a ball and then it
took him 10 years more or something like
that he offered a bowl and nothing in
it cuz he's in a rush or something like
Circle K was
closed okay
CH he's describing uh we have like two
more minutes I'll just go through this
he's describing a uh a wrong way of
meditating on EMP I can lean for you she
got the sun in her I he's describing a
wrong way of meditating on so here it is
and apparent every time he does that it
means somebody in Tibet was doing that
at the time okay usually there's someone
in every country doing that okay fair
enough you you think of a vase in your
mind you say the word vase water piter
okay in Tibet a water pitcher was the
most common example in a monastic
setting
why it didn't have
pipes okay you sent your disciples to
the well whether it was a mile away or
50 ft away and they came back with a
water picture whole water and you used
it throughout the day and then so every
room had a water picture in it okay
books of shag think of water picture in
your
mind to take away the lip the what do
you call
that yeah it's more like the
uh the yeah the rim it's the rim it's
the FL Rim okay
uh that's not the that's not the vase
right the the edge of the rim is not the
vase the uh base of the vase is not the
B not the Bas sh so
chinny a silhouette par take away all
the pieces of the base take away the
handle take away the spout take away the
rim take away the B and what do you
got now I me remove them and throw them
out yeah well they thought that was
emptiness okay they they they
misunderstood the meaning of emptiness
okay they they thought oh the way to
arrive at emptiness is to just take away
the parts just throw off throw away
Parts until nothing's left and that's
emptiness okay that's wrong all
right and when you can't find a vase at
the end of that process don't need to
call they understood that as being
EMP and then they pretended to meditate
on that he was
like you know then they they thought
they
[Music]
meditating we pick up on let's start off
okay so we'll meet again
at what time
five what time is it now it's 4:45
right it's 3:45 sorry did I stop at the
right
time oh God bless okay
sorry I'm sorry you had so much hope
okay
rather so they took a a thing which they
were trying to establish this being
empty uh take a take a thing like the
pen and then figure out what's the pen
that's not there and that's the correct
process okay but rather without doing
that they fell into the emptiness where
nothing was there which is not the
correct emptiness you don't arrive at
emptiness by taking all the people out
of the room and saying okay that's
emptiness
okay that's not going to liberate you
okay it's not going to liberate you to
say there's no pen there rather it's
going to liberate you to say there's no
pen there that's not coming from me then
I can make my own pens and I can change
my life or my body or anything
so people were kind of making up their
own kinds of emptiness concocted
emptinesses artificial
emptinesses
therefore people like us we talked about
that phrase in tibetan what was it
People Like
Us
do or R do ja or R and it's used by high
llamas to be friendly because we're not
like them okay but they say People Like
Us guys they say us guys in tibetan and
it's considered a joke in the monastery
you know like the Dil will say us guys
and everybody's like yeah that's good
you know okay uh all right
when we are looking for the thing that's
not there right because that's our job
today we are looking for what's not
there we're looking for the credit
card that's we're looking for what is a
credit card because you can't understand
that you don't have a credit card if you
don't know credit card is be aware that
we are now dealing with credit cards
that never
existed we're not dealing with credit
cards that ever did exist it's like a
Discover Card
okay okay
I have one and nobody takes it it's
really fun
uh it's just mostly for opening
locks and uh scraping ice off your
windshield J tell that I think that's
why they send it to you okay n no but
that's a good example because it's a
bogus credit card you see and and we're
talking about bogus M bogus M okay all
right
say how is it that
our he's going to start talking about
say
n it's good if you spit when you say
okay
n
10K okay it means uh 10K is an important
word
uh what is it in sah in Sanskrit sah
means in built in John means born so h
means uh inborn you were born with it
you were born with it you were born with
a certain way of looking at the world
which is
wrong you were born with a certain way
of looking at the world which is
wrong and everybody has it if you're in
this realm you and you're not a dad
disguised which you all are but
anyway I have it okay gotcha so
how is it exactly what am I doing wrong
about the door that's all what am I
doing wrong about M how am I
misperceiving m just tell me and I'll
stop
okay we must look into this question we
must look into this
question we have to examine two
things how does Mike appear to Mike's
mind right
okay from the object sign how does how
does Mike appear to Mike's mind and how
is Mike's mind taking that object okay
so there's two things how is it what's
the incoming in data right how is Mike
appearing to that wrong state of mind
and then how am I interpreting it that
data incoming data and interpretation of
the data how how is mik appearing to mik
and how does mik take mic wrongly those
are two subjects we have to look into
[Music]
this is one of the most powerful
sentences in this book okay it's really
beautiful
[Music]
okay I want to get it right
thinking of themselves in the wrong way
not just with regard to their individual
Parts but with the whole M okay uh
seeing the whole M as if it's incoming
right seeing Mike as if Mike is coming
this way
okay and thinking that's me seeing Mike
as if Mike existed this way and
might
okay exists in all living creatures from
ants
on even ants have
it even ants are misunderstanding
themselves okay even an ant even the
most primitive State of Consciousness is
still holding things the wrong way okay
all forms of life from the most
primitive kinds of life even amibas are
are mix up with their ability to sense
heat cold enemy friend is mixed up a
misunderstanding of who they
are how they take the hall and and don't
take and don't and don't think okay
about what it is everybody has it bugs
have it
okay and even in their dreams even down
to their dreams okay not even just their
waking consciousness okay from Bugs on
up from dreams on up it's very powerful
in fact okay I'll say
it you know from from dream on up we're
all misunderstanding who we
[Music]
areu means deep in their heart yep
that's the that's the misunderstanding
of me that I was born I came into this
life with it okay we all came into this
life with it
I'll start but we won't get through this
part okay
but we got to use our time right to get
Rebecca to sit down and call this all
these places and I mean how often is
that going to happen Okay so we got to
grab the time you know once we're all
heated and slapped and E eat it and yog
good we should do something okay uh
because that the time left over is very
small
[Music]
there there are three ways in which you
can think of me so get this get this
down okay there are three ways in which
Eric can think of Eric or jig can think
of jig or Carl can think of Carl or
Jason can think of Jason okay there's
three ways
L the first one is the good one okay the
first one is the good way to look at
yourself people who have had some
education in what Emptiness
is they look at a pen as being a blue
object which their the seas in their
mind have compelled them to see as a p
that's all okay
they look upon a pen they view a pen as
a collection of colors and shapes which
they're the seeds in their own mind are
compelling them to see as a
pen but they're doing it with me okay a
well-trained person is saying I see a
mortal arm I see skin Blood and
Bone uh about Mike I look at Mike's arm
I see skin Blood and
Bone but I understand that the reason I
see
mortality is is is because I have not
respected
life
a I I have not respected life
enough okay would you go to a fine
restaurant if they had a chicken chain
to the table and you had to slit his
throat to eat it you know would you do
it you know would you kill a cow in the
corner of the restaurant with your own
hands would you choke a cow with your
own hands
whatever you know to eat it uh this is
the that those seeds of all
the double Whoppers you ever ate are uh
are causing you to see this Mortal okay
and so a well-trained person sees Mike
sees Mike as as collections of Parts
which are interpreted in a certain way
by the Mind due to my kindness or lack
of kind get it do the SE in my mind all
right that's the good person all right R
and chck that's
one then
make and they discount its
unreality they they appreciate it
unreality meaning what it didn't have to
be skin and
bone okay skin and bone is unreal it
could have been
light it could have been something else
they discount it its reality they say
look it's not really real is it it could
have been something else if I had if I
had different seeds in my mind it could
have been something else they they don't
take it as fixed and unfixable fixed
that's good that'll be the title of my
next
album they don't take it as fixed and
unfixable okay they don't they don't
take it that way all right all right
way of looking at M number two the first
one is the intelligent one right the
second one is the common person just
regular
people uh just normal
people uh they they look in the and they
say there's mine okay they're not like
uh what do you call analyzing it they're
not uh refuting pran gikas and
supporting South trtica you know like
they're not
like jup mala means they have not been
polluted by philosophical schools okay
they're like okay there's Mike what do
you want me to do you know all right
who's in the mirror it's Mike you know
does he exist I don't know it's just
there okay all right that one way of
there's the mic that appears that way
when you look in the mirror and you're
not analyzing
okay can't maer you're not trying to see
if it exists from its own side or not
okayer so that's second way of looking
at me unfortunately you have enough time
to start the third
way and then there's a third one where
if somebody asks you is he coming from
his own side you
say
yes yeah he is so that's a hardcore
wrong view right somebody ask you to
analyze it they they they they ask you
to dig into it is Ningbo the Ningbo you
thought it was and you you
go yes doesn't exist from out side well
where else you know okay then that's
like a what do you call Active wrong you
the second one is just sort of a you
know
[Music]
callely all
right
[Music]
sorry I'm just going to finish the
sentence okay I'm not trying to hold you
here
number two is a
PR number two is a reasonable State of
Mind number two is valid what was number
two hey it's just
John not questioning whether he came
from his own side or not just what the
person we normally deal with it's just
John just John he calls it n which means
just me so you just replace the with any
person you are
okay just bny that's just bny okay you
see anything in Mirror yeah who is it me
okay that's a pman that's a correct
perception that's not wrong and that's
not
harmful is does Ellen exist yes did she
go to tyan yes did she do a nice job yes
we have to discuss it you know no she's
there she was there sorry
okay anyway so
any that's a state of mind which
is establishing a certain me and it's
correct relatively
speaking the the mic which that state of
mind is perceiving exists it's really
there okay to he brushes his teeth he
Combs his hair he you know Etc
okay this is very
important he can also be the person who
who undertakes actions who creates
karmas and under goes the results of
those karmas okay that's fine John in
the mirror unexamined is reasonably the
person who will do things and who will
undergo the consequences of those
actions that's
okay one more sentence and we're done we
might we might as well right okay my
leg's about to Charlie okay don't
mind I'm gonna skip the number he says
number blank okay you have to fill in
number blank
is the me which we want to deny which we
want to stop which we want to stop
thinking exists which one number two
okay he is coming from my I do come from
my
side pen does come from the
pen if you truly understood that the pen
didn't come from the pen how upset would
you get when the dog chewed
on not much yeah still get upset I think
but uh it's a good answer
uh but you would sympathize with the dog
empathize you would say okay I
understand your seeds are different you
see something to chew on you know
whether you would still agree with them
chewing on it I don't know but at least
you would not get get so upset right you
could understand you could see the other
person's point of view you got your
seeds I got mine I understand you wanted
Che on it you know now stop that okay
all right but initi you want to get
upset all right we'll stop there and
we'll we'll do some
more and
yeah we'll have some announcements after
the after we create a perfect world okay
[Music]
the
sh sh
[Music]
okay it's a beautiful text I mean it's
probably the most beautiful scripture I
think it's cool right all right uh Becky
is going to make some announce